<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief account of the virtues of the famous well of Astrop, not far from Oxford, of late so much frequented by the nobility and gentry. By a learned physician</title>
            <author>Lower, Richard, 1631-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49321</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3307A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216632</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828357</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828357</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32784</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49321)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32784)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1928:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief account of the virtues of the famous well of Astrop, not far from Oxford, of late so much frequented by the nobility and gentry. By a learned physician</title>
                  <author>Lower, Richard, 1631-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year MDCLXVIII. [1668]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A learned physician = Richard Lower. Attribution from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mineral waters --  England --  Astrop --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32784:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 35 -->
            <p>A BRIEF ACCOUNT OF THE VIRTUES OF THE Famous Well OF ASTROP, Not far from <hi>Oxford,</hi> of late ſo much frequénted by the NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BILITY and GENTRY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Learned Phyſician.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year MDCLXVIII.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32784:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 36 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:32784:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 36 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account_of_healing_properties">
            <pb facs="tcp:32784:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32784:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
            <head>A Brief Account of the famous Well of <hi>Aſtrop,</hi> not far from <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His WELL riſeth on the ſide of a Hill in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrop,</hi> a Village belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>King's Sutton</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> but joyning to <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſhire,</hi> three mile from <hi>Banbury.</hi> It was dedicated to S. <hi>Rumbald</hi> a Child which ſpake ſo ſoon as he was born. It yields an Iron water participating of Vitriol, as all Iron doth.</p>
            <p>It openeth, aſtringeth, and conſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dateth egregiouſly: it abſtergeth viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous and tartarous Humours in the Stomack, Meſenteric, <hi>Hypochondria,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:32784:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->Reins, Ureters, and Bladder, and opens the Obſtructions of thoſe parts: it penetrates through every occult paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage where other Medicines cannot come.</p>
            <p>It dries up the Defluxions and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillations of the Head, and by this means takes away the old and long continued Headach <hi>Vertigo,</hi> Palſey, Convulſion, Trembling, Darkneſs of the Sight, and watering of the Eyes, and all ſorts of the Gout: it cures mattery and running Eares, too much Spitting and Moiſtneſs of the Mouth.</p>
            <p>By abſorbing and taking away the excrementitious Humidities of the Brain, it preſerveth from an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexie: it alters a relax'd and weak Stomack, ſtirs up the Appetite, and confirms the Retentive Faculty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32784:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->it ſtays often Vomiting, the <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lericus Morbus,</hi> Diarrhoea, Dyſenterie or Bloudy-flux, and Lienterie: it kills Worms in young and old, and expels them.</p>
            <p>It opens the Obſtructions of the Liver and Spleen, cures the <hi>Flatus hypochondriacus,</hi> and the Palpitation and Trembling of the Heart proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from thence: it is a certain reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for the Scurvy: it faſtens the Teeth, though ready to drop out: it cures Aches and Cramps in any part of the Body whatſoever, and giveth great eaſe therein ſuddenly.</p>
            <p>It opens all Obſtructions, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth all Overflowings in Women, ſtrengthens the Womb, and is a great help to Conception, and preventative againſt Miſcarrying: it cures the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32784:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->and Precipitation of the Matrix, and falling down of the Fundament.</p>
            <p>It extirpates Agues of long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, cures the Jaundice and Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy in the beginning, eſpecially if from a hot Cauſe: it helps the Green-ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and reſtores a freſh and lively Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour to the Face.</p>
            <p>It takes away the ſwelling and pains of the Spleen, expells the Stone and Sand: but eſpecially it helps the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities of the Bladder, as the Exul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceration thereof, Strangury, and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of making water, and the invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary paſſing away of the water, the piſſing of Bloud, and the Gonorrhoea.</p>
            <div n="bathing" type="part">
               <head>In Bathing,</head>
               <p>It comforts the Nerves and relax'd Joynts, helps the Gout, confirms a ſlippery Matrix, and prevents Abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32784:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->it ſtrengthens broken Bones and Members out of joynt, and diſcuſſeth the Tumours that ſucceed thoſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, cures the Scab and <hi>Impetigo,</hi> ſtays the falling down of the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the immoderate flowing of the <hi>Menſes,</hi> and the Haemorrhoids.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="lotion" type="part">
               <head>By Lotion,</head>
               <p>It helps many Diſeaſes of the Eyes, the aſperity of the Eye-lids, the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling off of the Hair, and the running Sores of the Head.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="injection" type="part">
               <head>By Injection,</head>
               <p>The Diſeaſes of the Wombe, Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament, and Bladder.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
